Mss.B.R124
American Philosophical Society
C. S. (Constantine Samuel) Rafinesque correspondence and writings, 1808-1840
Mss.B.R124
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet Ca. 400 items
The correspondence is principally to Zaccheus Collins (1810-1840), with bills, receipts, and notes on Rafinesque vs. Parker; letters from Collins, L.A. Tarascon, Lewis C. Beck, John Torrey, and Charles W. Short (1817-1835); and miscellaneous correspondence and documents relating to Rafinesque vs. Parker, with an account of the Felician Society of Feliciana County, Illinois (1820). The writings are chiefly on botanical topics, and include notes and essays on Indians, Blacks, grapes and wine-making, banking, and speculation. Rafinesque's growing interest in Indian antiquities, linguistics, and history is apparent in letters after 1820. There is an account of Rafinesque's scientific travels in North America and southern Europe (1800-1832), and a bibliography. The botanical notes include descriptions of specimens collected by Lewis and Clark, Patrick Gass, and Henry Muhlenberg.
Ca. 400 items.
Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840
Box 1
Related Archival Materials note
Associated materials at the American Philosophical Society: Ancient monuments of North and South America, 1822-1825 (Film 32). Letters to John Torrey, 1819-1840 (Film 898). Correspondence with William Swainson (Film 898.1).
African American History Note
The collection contains a manuscript written for a contest sponsored by the Societe de Geographie de Paris. The organization sought the best-written history of the "origins of negroes." Rafinesque was awarded a gold medal for his work.
Rafinesque, Constantine S. Memoires sur l'origine des nations negres, ou introduction a l'histoire des negres indigenes d'Asie, d'Afrique, polynesie, Amerique et Europe. 1831. 1 item (106 pages).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Deposited by the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia and accessioned, 1943.
Biographical/Historical note
Constantine Samuel Rafinesque-Schmaltz (1783-1840) was a self-educated naturalist, archaeologist, linguist and entrepreneur. Although scorned or ignored by many contemporaries, his adoption of “natural” botanical classifications consistent with the theory of organic evolution was in advance of his time. He was a founding member of the New York Lyceum of Natural History. A linguist and archaeologist of Mesoamerica, he made important archaeological investigations of ancient native American earthworks in Ohio and Kentucky and made some of the first investigations of ancient Mayan script. In volume 1 of his two-volume work American Nations Rafinesque claimed to have discovered an account of Lenni Lenape origins. The Walam Olum, considered authentic by many ethnohistorians at the time, was exposed as a fabrication in the late twentieth century. Rafinesque’s most financially successful work was the Medical Flora, a Manual of the Medical Botany of the United States of North America (1828-30).
Rafinesque was born in Galata, a suburb of Constantinople. He was the son of a French merchant Georges F. Rafubesque, originally from Marseilles and Madeleine Schmaltz, a native Greek woman of German extraction. The family returned to Marseilles, but after his father’s death in 1793, his mother fled with her three children from the French Revolutionary Reign of Terror to Leghorn, Italy, where they lived until 1796. After this he lived successively in Pisa, Genoa and Marseilles until 1800. Rafinesque had little education, except from private tutors. But, by the age twelve, he could read botanical Latin and began collecting plants for a herbarium.
In 1802 at the age of nineteen Rafinesque began an apprenticeship with the Clifford brothers, who were merchants in Philadelphia. In Philadelphia he met physician Benjamin Rush (1745-1813, APS 1768) (whose student he declined to become), the horticulturalist Thomas Forrest, and naturalists Moses Marshall and William Bartram (1739-1823, APS 1768). Over the next two and a half years the young man roamed the country-side collecting specimens of flora and fauna. He also collected reptiles for François Daudin’s Natural History of Reptiles (1802-03). In November 1804 Rafinesque wrote to Jefferson to inquire why no botanist was included on the Dunbar expedition to the Red River Valley expedition. However, he left for Italy before the President could respond, offering him the position.
Between 1805 and 1815 Rafinesque lived in Sicily, for three years serving as secretary to the American Consul in Palermo. He made a fortune in a part-time business enterprise, selling medical squills for export. Having become financially secure, he retired at age 25, hoping to devote his life to the pursuit of natural history. Rafinesque considered the ten years he spent in Sicily, the best years of his life. He married Josephine Vaccaro, who bore him two children, but his protestant faith prevented the union from being recognized. In 1810 he published his first book, Caratteri di alcuni nuovi generi e nuove specie di animali e piante della Sicilia, which set the mold for many of his subsequent works, namely a classification and description of new species of plants and animals. During 1814 he edited and published a monthly scientific journal called the Specchio delle scienze (Mirror of Science), reputed to be the first in Sicily. In order to become better known on the Continent as a naturalist, in 1815 he published an Analyse de la nature, which was modeled upon Linnaeus’s Systema naturae, but written in French, the language he thought would soon become the medium of science. An unsuccessful bid for the chair of botany at the University of Palermo that year led Rafinesque to return to the United States in 1815.
Rafinesque’s return voyage to America ended in a shipwreck off the Long Island coast in which he lost “everything”—his books, manuscripts and drawings. Later, ashore in New York he was befriended by Samuel Latham Mitchill the physician, naturalist and politician, who introduced him to other naturalists. Two years later in 1817 Rafinesque was one of the founding members of New York’s Lyceum of Natural History. Also, that year he published his controversial Florula Ludoviciana, that introduced a “natural” system of botanical classification based upon the models of French naturalists Michel Adanson and Antoine de Jussieu, who grouped plants on the basis of perceived morphological relationships instead of the “artifical” Linnaean system then prevalent in America. He was also criticized for naming and classifying plants in the volume that he had never seen, relying on a published account of the French botanical writer C.C. Robin.
In the spring of 1818 Rafinesque mounted a major collecting trip down the Ohio River to describe all of its fish, resulting in the publication of Ichthyologia Ohiensis. Although this was the first such attempt at a description of Ohio River fish, the manuscript, as well as a series of papers on Ohio mollusks was spurned by Silliman’s American Journal of Science and Arts. Rafinesque also ran into trouble with the referees of the Journal of the Academy of Natural Sciences for submitting a paper, whose substance he had published elsewhere. As a result of these negative experiences, he increasingly turned to self-publications. Despite these setbacks, he made another important 2,000 mile tour to collect botanical specimens beyond the Alleghenies as far west as Kentucky and Illinois. By 1818, he had collected and named more than 250 new species of plants and animals.
In 1819 Rafinesque accepted a professorship in botany at Transylvania University in Lexington, Kentucky, where an old Philadelphia merchant friend John D. Clifford was a trustee. Despite a stormy seven-year tenure, Rafinesque was awarded an honorary Master of Arts by Transylvania in 1822, and shortly thereafter received an honorary doctorate from the Imperial Academy of Bonn (Germany). Leaving the university in 1826, Rafinesque returned to Philadelphia with forty crates of specimens and books, that served his research needs for the remainder of his life.
While in Kentucky Rafinesque began research on the indigeneous peoples of the Americas. In an 1822 publication he made the first attempt at deciphering Mayan ideographs, suggesting that they were partly syllabic. He also investigated the prehistoric earthen mounds of the Ohio Valley and attempted to trace the movement of native American tribes by comparative studies of their languages. The most important publication to result from this research was the two-volume American Nations that appeared in 1836. An especially important section of the work was Rafinesque’s account of the origins of the Lenape (Delaware) Indians, who migrated to the lands around the Delaware River. He claimed that the account, known as the Walam Olum, was based on pictographs engraved and painted onto wooden sticks or plates together with a transcription of the Lenape language. These original tablets and the transcription were later lost, according to Rafinesques, leaving only his notes and a copy of the transcription. Although always controversial, many scholars considered the Walam Olum an authentic Native American account for well over a century after its “discovery”. Subsequent linguistic, ethnohistorical and archaeological analysis in the 1980’s and 1990’s tended to suggest it was a fabrication, an assessment that was confirmed by the 1995 thesis of David Oestreicher, The Anatomy of the Walam Olum: A 19th Century Anthropological Hoax.
Back in Philadelphia, Rafinesque once again edited a scientific quarterly journal; this one entitled the Atlantic Journal (1832-33). In 1832 he became a naturalized United States citizen, and also organized a small savings bank. Interspersed among the scientific publications of these final years of his life, were a number humanistic writings. One of these was a lengthy poem on mutability, entitled The World (1836). This was followed two years later by a linguistic analysis of the Genius and Spirit of the Hebrew Bible (1838). His most financially rewarding publication was the Medical Flora, a Manual of the Medical Botany of the United States of America (1828-30), but his other notable botanical works from this period include New Flora and Botany of North America (1836-38), Flora telluriana (1837-38), Sylva telluriana (1838) and Autikon botanikon (1840).
Although not wealthy, Rafinesque was comfortably established in Philadelphia at the end of his life. Despite receiving the best medical care the times could afford, he died of stomach cancer on September 18, 1840. His lifeswork was totally ignored by most of his contemporaries; nevertheless, most agreed with the sentiments expressed by botanist L.D. Schweintz, who wrote that “he is doubtless a man of immense knowledge—as badly digested as may be & crack-brained I am sure.” In his works, he proposed hundreds of new genera and thousands of new species, but his reputation would not be rehabilitated until the mid-twentieth century, when botanists acknowledged that the 6,700 Latin plant names he assigned were validated according to rules since adopted by botanists themselves. In 1924, Rafinesque’s remains were moved to Transylvania University. Unfortunately, many of his papers were damaged or destroyed after his death.
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: Over 200 ink sketches of linguistic pictographs of the Osage, Ojibwa, Ottawa, and Delaware tribes, transcribed by Rafinesque-Schmaltz in 1833. Entitled Graphic systems of America, the symbols are noted with English translations. The Lenape (Delaware) pictographs are associated with the controversial work Walam Olum. Referenced in Murphy’s Historical American Sketches and Freeman’s Guide to manuscripts relating to the American Indian.
Other Finding Aids note
For a description of the collection, see Charles Boewe, "The Manuscripts of C. S. Rafinesque (1783-1840)," APS Proceedings 102 (1958): 590-595.
Early American History Note
The Rafinesque Collection consists of two types of documents: correspondence and copies of his writings. The correspondence is separated into three distinct parts: general correspondence, correspondence with Augustin Pyramus de Candole (a Swiss botanist), and correspondence with John Quincy Adams. The copies of his writings consist of manuscript essays, notebooks, lectures, and other materials that discuss various scientific topics, especially botany.
The general correspondence takes up a box of material. The majority of letters are addressed to Zaccheus Collins, a Philadelphia merchant, although there are various letters to others. His early letters discuss the founding of a Lyceum in New York in 1817, while later letters (and the vast majority of the collection) discuss his botanical findings, travels, reading habits, and, on occasion, finance, especially his “divital invention” to fund internal improvements.
The letters to de Candole are all photocopies of letters at other archives and in French. The Adams correspondence consists of a single long letter addressed to Adams as Secretary of State that discusses botany, Indian linguistics, and cryptography.
His writings take up three boxes. There is an essay written in French in 1831 on the origins of indigenous peoples, which may have content relevant to the Walam Olum. There is also a document on the “Graphic Systems of North America,” which contains some of the symbols from the Walam Olum.
General note
Inventory incomplete. Please see finding aid in reading room.
Beck, Lewis C. (Lewis Caleb), 1798-1853; Collins, Zaccheus, 1764-1831; Gass, Patrick, 1771-1870; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815; Short, Charles Wilkins, 1794-1863; Tarascon, L. A.; Torrey, John, 1796-1873; Bibliographies.; Biology, genetics, eugenics; Botany.; Culture, community, organizations; Delaware Indians; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Essays.; Europe -- Description and travel.; Indians of North America--Louisiana; International Travel; Journals (notebooks).; Manuscript Essays; Native America; Native American Materials; Natural History; North America -- Description and travel.; Notebooks; Ojibwa Indians; Osage Indians; Ottawa Indians; Picture-writing; Plains Indians; Political Correspondence; Race, race relations, racism; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Sketches.; Travel; Wallam olum; Zoology.
- Papers
  - Plates of C.S. Rafinesque, 1808; 8" x 13 1/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Scope and Contents note
    select new plants of North America. A.D.S. 4p.
  - Med. repository, 1808-1811; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Raf. A.D. 23p. (Appears to be writings by Rafinesque which appeared in the Medical repository, 1808-1811)
    General note
    Unlocated 3/11
  - Letter to Samuel Mitchill, July 4, 1810; 8 1/4" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Palermo, A.L.S. 4p. end.
  - 1816 Somiological memorandum, Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840
  - Distinctions generiques parmi les plantes monocotyles de L'Amerique septentrionale, observee entre 1816 & 1830, Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840
  - Avis à mettre dans les gazettes savoir l'Aurora & Poulson's pendent une semaine., September 15, 1816; 8 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    New York, A.D.S. 4p. In French and English. Re agents for a banking speculation.
  - Florula albionesis, or plants of NW coast y Lewis & Clarke, Clarke, William Branwhite, 1798-1878; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809
  - Plants of Dr. Muhlenberg-western country, [Circa 1817]
  - [Plants of] Lewis & Clarke Missouri--plants of Gass, Plants of Brackenridge, [Circa 1817]; Clarke, William Branwhite, 1798-1878; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809
  - Plants of the Missouri territory bound by Mr. Bradbury near the lead mines on the Merimack which falls in the Mississippi 36 miles below the forks., [Circa 1817]
  - Florula Mandanensis Plants of Missouri by Lewis and Pursh, [Circa 1817]; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809
  - Plants Missouri-Lewis & Clarke, Michaux, [Circa 1817]; Clarke, William Branwhite, 1798-1878; Lewis, Meriwether, 1774-1809
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, March 15, 1817; 8 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    New York, A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, July 21, 1817; 8 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
  - C.S. Rafinesque to the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadlephia, 1817 August 9
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, October 18, 1817; 8 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    New York, A.L.S. 2p. and add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, November 1, 1817; 8 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
  - Letter to [C.S.] Rafinesque, November 10, 1817; 7 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Collins, Zaccheus, 1764-1831
    Philadelphia A. copy of L.S. with initials. 3p. and end.
  - Letter to [C.S. Rafinesque], November 19, 1817; 7 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Collins, Zaccheus, 1764-1831
    Philadelphia, A.L. 2p. (incomplete)
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, November 27, 1817; 8 1/4" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
  - Note relative to books sent to S.W. Conrad to be accounted for by him with C.S. Rafinesque, December 6, 1817; 6 1/4" x 7 3/4"; Collins, Zaccheus, 1764-1831
    A.N.S. with initials. 2p.
  - Letter to Z[accheus] Collins, December 27, 1817; 8 1/4" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    New York, A.L.S. 7p.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, December 28, 1817; 8 1/4" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    New York, A.L.S. 1p. and add.
  - Prod. de 50 N.G. de plantes observees dans l'int. des Etats Unis en 1817 & 1818, 1817-1819
  - Florula Mandanensis, or Description of several new plants collected by Mr. Bradbury near the Mandan nation., 1817-1820
  - Neocloris, or descriptions of new plants by C.S. Rafinesque, all in my herbarium Begun New York 1817 (continue to 1825), 1817-1825; Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840
  - Nova genera plantarum vascularum Americanum, or New genera of vasular plants from the United States., [Circa 1818]
  - Catalogus; 150 plantae novae vel rariora Kentuckienses, 1818-1822
  - Plantes rares ou nouvelles observées en., 1818; 8 1/2" x 12"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    A.D. 4p. In French.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, June 1, 1818; 7 3/4" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Pittsburg, A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, July 20, 1818; 7 3/4" x 9 1/2"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Falls of the Ohio, A.L.S. 4p. add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, August 12, 1818; 7 1/2" x 12 1/2"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Henderson, Ky., A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, November 6, 1818; 7 3/4" x 9 1/2"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Pittsburgh, A.L.S. 4p. add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, December 4, 1818; 8" x 9 1/2"; Torrey, John, 1796-1873
  - [List of new genera of animals and plants], May 1, June 1, 1819; 8" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    A.D. 2p. In French.
  - Letter to Robert Wickliff, February 11, 1819; 8 1/2" x 11"; Clifford, John D., 1778?-1820
    Lexington, Typed c. of L. 1p. (Original at Transylvania College)
  - Letter to Robert Wickliffe, April 25, 1819; 8 1/2" x 11"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Philadelphia, Typed c. of L. 1p. (Original at Transylvania College)
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, September 25, 1819; 8 1/4" x 9 1/2"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - C.S. Rafinesque to Samuel L Mitchill (species of the genus Clintonia), 1819 Sept 26; Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, December 1, 1819; 8 1/2" x 9 1/2"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Ky., A.L.S. 2p. and add.
  - New or rare plants of Kentucky, [Circa 1820]
  - Descriptions of Hedychloe frangans, Melacinus parviflorus and Xeromallon obovatum, [Circa 1820]
  - Felician society in Feliciana cy., 1820; 8 1/2" x 12 1/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Illinois state.... A.D. 8p.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, February 10, 1820; 8 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Ky., A.L.S. 1p. and add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, April 20, 1820; 8" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Ky., A.L.S. 3p. and add.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, June 25, 1820; 8" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
  - Letter to Z[accheus] Collins, July 15, 1820; 8" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Ky., A.L.S. 1p. and end.
  - Certificate issued to C.S. Rafinesque, conferring upon him the name "Catesbaeus", November 28, 1820; 20 1/2" x 16"; Caesareae Leopoldino-Carolinae academiae naturae curiosorum.
    Bonn, Printed D. 1p.
  - Letter to C.S. Rafinesque, February 15, 1821; 8" x 9 3/4"; Hart, John A.
    Natchez, A.L.S. 2p. and add. Enclosure (3p.)
  - Descriptions de 2N. Geres d'Ombelliferes a feuilles simples observes dans la Kentucky, 1822; Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840
  - New species of plants discovered., 1822
  - Bill for $44 issued to the Trustees of Transylvania university, for board and sundries, January, 1822; 8 1/2" x 11"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Transylvania university, Typed c. of D. 1p. (original at Transylvania College)
  - Bill for $55 issued to Transylvania university for board and candles, September, 1822; 8 1/2" x 11"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Typed c. of D. 1p. (Original at Transylvania College)
  - Bill for $60 issued to Transylvania university for board and candles, October, 1822; 8 1/2" x 11"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Typed c. of D. 1p. (Original at Transylvania college)
  - Letter to the Board of trustees of Transylvania University, May 1, 1822; 8" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Transylvania university, A.L.S. 4p.
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, September 24, 1822; 8 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Ky., A.L.S. 4p. add.
  - Report of Committee on the communications of Prof. Rafinesque [submitted to the Board of trustees of the Transylvania university], 1823; 8 1/2" x 11"; Chapman, George T. (George Thomas), 1786-1872
    [ca.] Typed D. 1p. (Original at Transylvania College)
  - Letter to the Board of trustees of Transylvania university, April 5, 1823; 8 1/2" x 11"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
  - Letter to [C.S.] Rafinesque, July 2, 1823; 8 1/4"x10"; Collins, Zaccheus, 1764-1831
    A.Dr. of L.S. with initials. 2p. (Mutilated)
  - Letter to Zaccheus Collins, August 25, 1823; 8" x 9 3/4"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, Ky., A.L.S. 4p. add. Offers manuscript on monuments of Kentucky and Indian history if APS wishes to follow up Heckewelder publication. Mentions collections of comparative vocabularies and numerals.
  - Letter to the Board of trustees of Transylvania university, December 1, 1823; 8 1/2" x 11"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Transylvania university, Typed c. of L. in 3d P. 1p. (Original at Transylvania College)
  - An account of the herbariums of Prof. C.S. Rafinesque..., 1st January, 1824; 7" x 9 1/2"; Rafinesque, C. S. (Constantine Samuel), 1783-1840
    Lexington, A.D. 4p.
  - Letter to J[ohn] Q[uincy] Adams, 1824 July 8 (Box 1)
    Copy of photocopy and negative photostat